Coronet Magazine Military History Project Records
Coronet Magazine Military History Project Records
1862-1970
4.5 linear ft.
Correspondence and memorabilia to, from, and about soldiers (Civil War through Korea)
2628698
Biographical History
Coronet Magazine was published from October 13, 1936 to March 1971 and ran for 299 issues.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Coronet Magazine Military History Project Records consists of correspondence and World War II material.
Correspondence consists of letters, postcards and other correspondence sent home by American soldiers in five wars -- Civil War, World War I, World War II, Vietnam, and Korea. There is also a Civil War diary for the year 1892 and extensive collections of letters from a World War I private and a World War II officer, as well as a small amount of memorabilia.
World War II in Europe items include a Nazi flag, a Nazi history book, aerial photographs, maps and newspapres/news clippings (e.g., 8 Dec 1942 with headline "JAPAN STARTS WAR.").
A small number of military pamphlets relating to Nuclear war complete the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically by war. World War II in Europe material is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Related Material
See also
Coronet Magazine Records
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Civil War (U.S.); Military history; Coronet -- Archives.; Korean War, 1950-1953 -- Personal narratives.; Military history -- United States.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Personal narratives.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives.; Nuclear warfare -- Pamphlets.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives.; Aerial photographs.; Sound recordings.; Books.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Maps (documents); Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Tape reels.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Access to audiorecordings requires advance notice to produce a use copy.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Esquire, Inc., 1961-62.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Civil War
    - Miscellanous writings, includes a diary and "Soldier's Pocketbook" (Box 1)
    - Memorabilia, buttons from uniform of Grand Army of the Republic (Oversize 3)
  - World War I
    - Miscellaneous, 1918; Garton S. Churchill, Floyd B. Bremerman, Russell Mustard, Leonard Pratt, Robert Bloomingdale and others; includes photographs and postcards (Box 1)
    - Snyder, John G., 1917-1920; letters to his father in Illinois; includes photographs (Box 1)
  - World War II
    - Churchill, S. Garton, 1942-1946; New York City attorney who wrote a serialized letter to soldiers on his mailing list, arranged as "volumes" bu him; contains both letters he wrote and letters sent to him by others; 2 volumes (Box 1)
    - Churchill, S. Garton, 1942-1946; New York City attorney who wrote a serialized letter to soldiers on his mailing list, arranged as "volumes" bu him; contains both letters he wrote and letters sent to him by others; 1 volume (Box 2)
    - Gifford, Jr., Eli G. ("Biz"), Captain, 1940-1945; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1942-1945; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Korea
    - Casey, Charles, letter from Casey, possibly transcribed by his mother Helen Long Casey as it is on her stationery, with notes at the end that talk about her son's death; also two letters from Casey's commanding officers (Box 3)
  - Viet Nam
    - Breslau, Roger C., 1969-1970; Air Force major and surgeon; letters to and from former patients and friends in the military (Box 4)
    - Farris, George K., 1966; letters to his parents (Box 4)
    - Foley, John B., 1965-1966; letters to Betsy Cran of Chicago and from Tony Puglio (Box 4)
    - Kempner, Marion Lee, 1942-1966; bound volume of letters from Lt. Kempner, self-published by his parents after his death as "Letters from Sandy" (Stinehour Press, Lunenberg, VT) (Box 4)
    - Unidentified, Tom to Janalee, 1968-1970 (Box 4)
    - Recording, "Dave Matloff #1", Sep 1967; coronet_mil_001; 1 3" reel (Box 5)
    - Recording, "Dave Matloff #2", Dec 1967; coronet_mil_002; 1 3" reel (Box 5)
    - Recording, "Dave Matloff #3", May 1968; coronet_mil_003; 1 3" reel (Box 5)
- World War II in Europe
  - Aerial photographs (Box 4)
  - "Graphic history of the 29th", one sheet with cartoons and humorous captions regarding the adventures of the 29th Infantry in Europe (Tube 1)
  - Magazines (Oversize 2)
  - Maps, large military-issue maps of areas in France and Germany, some with handwritten annotations and markings, including one hand-annotated as "Omaha Beach" (Tube 1)
  - Memorabilia, large Nazi banner, 2 framed photographs (Oversize 3)
  - Military manuals
    - Breaching the Siegfried Line, 2 volumes (Oversize 1)
    - Defenses of Brest, includes large oversize foldout map; various other items laid in (Oversize 1)
    - Mission accomplished (Oversize 1)
    - Normandy to the Elbe (Oversize 1)
  - News clippings (Oversize 4)
  - Photobook, Deutschland Erwacht (Germany Awakens), Cigaretten Bildendienst, Altona-Bahrenfeld, 1933; Third Reich propaganda book containing dozens of printed and tipped-in photos as well as a very large (4') foldout photo of a rally in Nuremberg; an early publishing effort by the Nazi Party shortly after Adolf Hitler was appointed Chancellor (Oversize 3)
  - Scrapbook, postcards (Oversize 1)
  - Scrapbook, postcards (Oversize 2)
- Nuclear war
  - Pamphlets, military (Box 4)